A Guide to the Mary Sinton Leitch Correspondence with J. J. Lankes, Ms2017-001
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Mary Sinton Leitch Correspondence with J. J. Lankes, 1932-1950
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Leitch, Mary Sinton, 1876-1954
Ms2017-001
0.2 Cubic Feet 1 box
The collection includes 27 letters (some with covers and envelopes) written by Mary Sinton Leitch to J. J. Lankes between 1932 and 1950. Introduced by a mutual friend, Leitch and Lankes maintained a more than 18-year correspondence that contained conversations of personal news & friends, the Virginia literary and art scene, and their own writing and artistic efforts (including Lankes collaborations with poet Robert Frost).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Mary Sinton Leitch Correspondence with J. J. Lankes was purchased by Special Collections in June 2015.
Biographical Note: Mary Sinton Leitch (1876-1954)
Mary Sinton Lewis was born in New York City, New York, in 1876 to Carlton Thomas and Nancy Dunlap McKeen Lewis. After attending Smith College and Columbia University, as well as schools in Europe, she worked in New York City, first as a women's prison inspector, and later as a contributing editor to several magazines and newspapers. In 1907, after taking some time to travel, she married John David Leitch and the couple settled in eastern Virginia. She helped to found the Poetry Society of Virginia, serving as both its president (1933) and co-president (1944-1945). She contined to service in editorial capacities, editing the Lyric Virginia Today (vol. 1), though writing became her larger focus. Between 1922 and 1952, she authored seven collections of poetry and short fiction: The Wagon and the Star (1922), The Unrisen Morrow (1926), The Black Moon (1929), Spider Architect (1937), From Invisible Mountains (1943), Himself and I (1950), and Nightingales on the Moon (1952). Leitch died in August 1954 and is buried in Virginia Beach, Virginia.
Many of her individual poems can be found online and a complete digitized version of The Wagon and the Star is available through the Internet Archive.
Source: Social Networks and Archival Context record for Leitch, Mary Sinton, 1876-1954
Biographical Note: J. J. Lankes (1884-1960)
Julius John (J. J.) Lankes was born in 1884 in Buffalo, NY. He began working as a draftsman in 1902, but spent the majority of his professional life known for his woodcuts. His career as an artist spanned decades, during which he created woodcuts and illustrations for authors, among others. In addition to Sherwood Anderson, he worked with Robert Frost and Beatrix Potter. Lankes wrote and illustrated A Woodcut Manual, published by Henry Holt in 1932. In 2006, The University of Tampa published a new edition of this book with selected letters and other writings, edited by Welford Dunaway Taylor. (A copy of the 2006 edition is housed in Special Collections. A copy of the 1932 edition is available at the University Libraries’ Art & Architecture Library.) In addition to his illustrations and work as an artist, Lankes taught at Wells College from 1933 to about 1940. From 1943 to 1950, Lankes worked for the reproduction section of the National Advisory Council for Aeronautics (NACA, later NASA). He retired in 1951 and died in April 1960.
Scope and Content
The collection includes 27 letters (some with covers and envelopes) written by Mary Sinton Leitch to J. J. Lankes between 1932 and 1950. Introduced by a mutual friend, Leitch and Lankes maintained a more than 18-year correspondence that contained conversations of personal news & friends, the Virginia literary and art scene, and their own writing and artistic efforts (including Lankes collaborations with poet Robert Frost). Leitch seemed to a center for social activity for writers and artists, hosting Lankes, Frost, Louis Jaffe, and others, and many of her letters include plans for events relating to the Poetry Society of Virginia.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials (in Virginia Tech Special Collections)
For additional materials relating to J. J. Lankes held by Special Collections, see:
The Welford D. Taylor Collection on Sherwood Anderson (Ms2015-020), includes correspondence between Anderson and Lankes, as well as between Anderson's widow, Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson and Lankes, and a variety of Anderson researchers and Lankes.
The Marvin H. Neel Papers, (Ms2016-022) contains biographical resources, ephemera, correspondence, and writings and woodcut prints by and related to Marvin H. Neel (1908-1978), created between 1933 and 1988, including letters and postcards to J. J. Lankes (1951-1961).
Related Materials (at other institutions)
Virginia Commonwealth University also includes papers of Mary Sinton Leitch. A finding aid for this collection is available online.
The Rauner Special Collections Library of Dartmouth University contains a collection of J. J. Lankes papers. A finding aid for the collection is available online.
Index Terms
Persons:
Frost, Robert, 1874-1963; Jaffe, Louis I. (Louis Isaac), 1888-1950; Lankes, Julius J., 1884-1960; Leitch, Mary Sinton, 1876-1954
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; American Literature -- Virginia
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence
Contents List
- June 18, 1932 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- July 13, 1939 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- March 24, 1940 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1941 (10 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1944 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1945 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1947 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- October 11, 1948 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- October 16, 1949 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1950 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 10)